## NAZMUS SHAKIB SAYOM

## CS EDUCATOR AND FULL STACK SYSTEM ENGINEER

msssayom.github.io
github.com/nsssayom

O Dhaka, Bangladesh in linkedin.com/in/nsssayom



#### ABOUT ME

A full-stack software developer specializing in Embedded Systems, IoT, Deep Learning, and Distributed Computing. Currently pursuing a teaching career to enrich my knowledge and to dedicate my energy and skills for the betterment of students as well as the institution.

#### **EDUCATION**

#### American International University-Bangladesh

BSc. in CSE | 2017 - 2020

- CGPA 3.96
- Summa Cum Laude
- Dean's List Award Spring, 2019
- Dean's List Award Fall, 2019

#### Lalmonirhat Govt. College

HSC from Science | 2015

• GPA 5.00

#### Lalmonirhat Govt. High School

SSC from Science | 2013

• GPA 5.00

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

#### Lecturer, Dept. of ETE/ICE

Daffodil International University | January 2022 - present

- Teaching
  - Embedded System Design
  - Operating Systems.
- On active research in IoT Lab on Embedded Hardware and TinyML.

## **Embedded Systems Engineer**

Hellotask | December 2020 - December 2021

- Designed and prototyping an IoT-enabled distributed advertising platform.
  - o Raspberry Pi, ESP32, GSM, GPS, NestJS, SocketlO, Next.js, Hasura
- Developed a full-stack voice call broadcasting platform
  - NestJS, TypeORM, Vue.js, Alpine.js
  - Alpha release live on: <u>dev.manydial.com</u>
- Designed and prototyped an IoT self-checkout general-purpose vending machine.
  - Raspberry Pi, Flask, SocketlO, RFID, PIR-sensor

#### **Embedded Systems Engineer (Contractual)**

Riseup Labs | June 2020 - December 2020

- Designed and prototyped a voice command-enabled remote controller for Walton Android TV.
  - Arduino, nRF24, IBM Watson speech to text API.
  - GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/nsssayom/VoiceRemoteTx">https://github.com/nsssayom/VoiceRemoteTx</a>
- Helped to maintain legacy backend applications.

#### Teaching Assistant (Internship)

- AIUB | January 2020 May 2020
- Teach and demonstrate Java Programming Language to undergrad students.

## **RESEARCH WORKS**

# A Deep Convolutional Neural Network-Based Approach to Classify and Detect Crack in Concrete Surface Using Xception.

Submitted for IC4RB 2021 | October 2021

## Disaster Victim Tracking and Rescue Support System with Failsafe Multilayer Communication Networks

Undergrad Thesis | May 2020

- ESP32, Node.js, LoRaWAN, BLE, GSM
- GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/nsssayom/last\_hope">https://github.com/nsssayom/last\_hope</a>

#### Realtime Indoor Positioning System Using Wireless Access Points

Academic Paper for Advanced Computer Networking Course | January 2020

#### Traffic Light Control Assistance for an Isolated Intersection in Dhaka City

Academic Paper for Research Methodology Course | May 2019

#### PERSONAL PROJECTS

#### OpenGaze: Web Service for OpenFace Facial Behaviour Analysis Toolkit

Personal Project | October 2021

- C++, Python, FastAPI, OpenFace, OpenCV
- GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/nsssayom/OpenGaze">https://github.com/nsssayom/OpenGaze</a>

#### Depen: A Handheld OCR and Word Definition Device

Human-Computer Interaction | January 2020

- Raspberry Pi Zero, I2C and SPI OLED Display, Python, OpenCV, WordNet Lexical Database
- GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/nsssayom/DePen">https://github.com/nsssayom/DePen</a>
- YouTube Demo: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=K\_XhoaMd00A">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=K\_XhoaMd00A</a>

#### Earth and Fire: A Deep Learning-Based Wildfire Forecasting Application

NASA Space App Challenge 2017 | April 2017

- Python, OpenCV, Tensorflow, PHP, JavaScript, PhoneGap
- GitHub: https://github.com/arman-bd/earth-and-fire

## TALK-E: A 2.4GHz Long Range Digital Walkie Talkie

Personal Project | June 2020

- nRF24L01+, Arduino, Audio Drivers, and Pre-amps
- GitHub: https://github.com/nsssayom/TALK-E

## Dancing Bees: A Data Visualization Application to Plot Flight Paths of Honey Bees

Data-Visualization | August 2020

- · Python, OpenCV
- GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/nsssayom/dancing-bees">https://github.com/nsssayom/dancing-bees</a>

#### Flight Delay Predictor Using Gradient Boosting

Academic Project | January 2020

- Python, TensorFlow
- GitHub: https://github.com/nsssayom/flight\_delay\_predictor

## **TECHNOLOGIES FAMILIAR WITH**

#### Languages

C/C++, Python, JavaScript, TypeScript, Java, C#, Visual Basic.NET, PHP, HTML, CSS

#### **Backend Frameworks**

Node.js, NestJS, Express, Fastify, TypeORM, Flask, FastAPI, Hasura

#### **Frontend Frameworks**

Next.js, React, Vue.js, Alpine.js, Bootstrap, Bulma

#### **OSs, DBs, Tools and Platforms**

Linux, RTOS, Git, MySQL, PostgreSQL, Nginx, AWS, Twilio, Basic Networking

#### **PCB** Design

Proteus, Fritzing

**MCUs** 

AVR, STM-32

SoCs

Raspberry Pi, Nvidia Jetson, ESP32

#### **Embedded Frameworks**

PlatformIO. Arduino

#### Communication

GSM, GPS, LoRa, nRF24

#### **AWARDS**

- AIUB CS Fest 2017 Champion on App Development
- AIUB Physics Quiz 2017 Champion
- Runners up, RU BFDC Freshers' Debate Competition, 2016
- Champion, CPSCR Inter-House Debate Competition 2014

### **REFERENCES**

#### Prof. Dr. Tabin Hassan

Professor & Head, Graduate Program (CS), Computer Science AIUB tabin@aiub.edu

### Hasan Basri Angel

Senior Software Engineer, Rakuten Group, Inc. Kawasaki, Kanagawa, Japan. angel\_bd2@yahoo.com